Arabic: بعدنلي أو بيت عدين كما يطلق عليها في العربية،
English Translation: Ba'dinli, or Beit Adin as it is called
in Arabic,
Arabic: أو عروس عفرين كما يحب أهلها أن يطلقوا عليها،
English Translation: or the Bride of Afrin, as its people
like to call it.
Arabic: قرية سورية تتبع ناحية راجو في منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب
الشمالي،
English Translation: A Syrian village belonging to the Rajo
sub-district in the Afrin region in the northern countryside
of Aleppo.
Arabic: وتبعد عن ناحية راجو 8 كيلومترات، وعن منطقة عفرين 20
كيلومتراً.
English Translation: It is 8 kilometers away from the Rajo
sub-district, and 20 kilometers away from the Afrin region.
Arabic: تابعونا في هذه الجولة من قرية بعدنلي التابعة لناحية
راجو.
English Translation: Join us on this tour of the village of
Ba'dinli, which belongs to the Rajo sub-district.
Arabic: بعدنلي، قرية سورية تتبع ناحية راجو في منطقة عفرين
شمالي حلب.
English Translation: Ba'dinli is a Syrian village belonging
to the Rajo sub-district in the Afrin region, north of
Aleppo.
Arabic: على بعد كيلومترين شرقها يمر خط حديد حلب ميدان إكيس
عند دخوله وادي النشاب.
English Translation: Two kilometers to its east passes the
Aleppo-Meydan Ekbis railway line as it enters the Al-Nashab
valley.
Arabic: تقع جنوبها قرية عرب أوشاغي وناحية معبطلي، وشمالها
سلسلة جبلية عالية وقرية درويش أوباسي.
English Translation: To its south lies the village of Arab
Ushaghi and the Maabatli sub-district, and to its north is a
high mountain range and the village of Darwish Obasi.
Arabic: بنيت القرية فوق هضبة، وتتجه بيوتها نحو الجنوب.
English Translation: The village was built on a plateau, and
its houses face south.
Arabic: وقد شُيدت على منحدر جبلي متدرج فوق بعضها البعض بحيث
أخذت شكل الهضاب الجبلية التي بنيت فوقها،
English Translation: They were built on a terraced mountain
slope, one above the other, taking the shape of the
mountainous plateaus they were built on.
Arabic: وتتداخل فيها الأبنية الأسمنتية الحديثة مع الأبنية
التقليدية القديمة المبنية من الحجر والطين والأسقف الخشبية.
English Translation: The modern cement buildings intertwine
with the old traditional buildings made of stone, mud, and
wooden roofs.
Arabic: العمر التاريخي للقرية قرابة 400 عام.
English Translation: The historical age of the village is
approximately 400 years.
Arabic: يعود أصل سكانها إلى عشيرة الشيخان الكردية، وكان يبلغ
عددهم قبل الثورة 5000 نسمة.
English Translation: The origin of its inhabitants goes back
to the Kurdish Sheikhan tribe, and their number before the
revolution was 5,000 people.
Arabic: لجأ 1500 منهم إلى أوروبا وتركيا، كما يسكن قسم آخر
منهم في مدينة حلب.
English Translation: 1,500 of them sought refuge in Europe
and Turkey, and another portion of them lives in the city of
Aleppo.
Arabic: نزحت إليها 400 عائلة سورية مهجرة من أرياف إدلب وريف
حمص الشمالي وجبل الزاوية وغوطة دمشق وغيرها.
English Translation: 400 displaced Syrian families from the
countrysides of Idlib, northern Homs, Jabal Al-Zawiya,
Ghouta of Damascus, and others have fled to it.
Arabic: يعمل أهالي القرية في الزراعة وخاصة الزيتون والجوز،
وكذلك في تجارة المحاصيل الزراعية مع القرى المجاورة.
English Translation: The people of the village work in
agriculture, especially olives and walnuts, as well as in
trading agricultural crops with neighboring villages.
Arabic: ويعتمد جزء منهم على التحويلات المالية من أبنائهم في
بلدان اللجوء.
English Translation: A portion of them rely on financial
remittances from their children in countries of asylum.
Arabic: يوجد في بعدنلي تعليم ومدارس حتى المرحلة الثانوية.
English Translation: Ba'dinli has education and schools up
to the high school level.
Arabic: يبلغ عدد سكان قرية بعدنلي 3500 نسمة،
English Translation: The population of the village of
Ba'dinli is 3,500 people,
Arabic: إضافة إلى 1500 من النازحين من كفر بطيخ في ريف إدلب،
English Translation: in addition to 1,500 displaced people
from Kafr Batikh in the Idlib countryside,
Arabic: والرستن في ريف حمص الشمالي، وغوطة دمشق ومناطق سورية
أخرى مختلفة.
English Translation: and Al-Rastan in the northern Homs
countryside, Ghouta of Damascus, and various other Syrian
areas.
Arabic: يشتهر سكان القرية بالتجارة في المحاصيل الزراعية
ويعملون في زراعة الأراضي وخاصة زراعة الزيتون.
English Translation: The residents of the village are famous
for trading agricultural crops and working in farming the
land, especially olive cultivation.
Arabic: سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في حارات وأزقة وأسواق قرية
بعدنلي، تابعونا.
English Translation: We will be with you in this segment in
the neighborhoods, alleys, and markets of the village of
Ba'dinli, stay tuned.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: وعليكم السلام.
English Translation: And peace be upon you.
Arabic: الله يعافيك، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God give you health.
English Translation: May God grant you health, welcome.
Arabic: الحمد لله، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: How are you?
English Translation: Praise be to God, welcome.
Arabic: نتعرف عليك؟
English Translation: Can we know your name?
Arabic: عارف علي بن إبراهيم.
English Translation: Aref Ali bin Ibrahim.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا، من بعدنلي؟
English Translation: Welcome, are you from Ba'dinli?
Arabic: شو بتشتغل؟
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: What do you do for a living?
Arabic: والله قديماً كنت نجار بيتون.
English Translation: Well, in the past I used to be a
concrete carpenter.
Arabic: حالياً؟
English Translation: Currently?
Arabic: هلق قاعد هلق.
English Translation: Right now, I am just sitting.
Arabic: قاعد.
English Translation: Just sitting.
Arabic: أنا والمرة، ما في حدا عندنا.
English Translation: Just me and the wife, we have no one
with us.
Arabic: الله يرزقك يا رب، وين ولادك؟
English Translation: May God provide for you, where are your
children?
Arabic: والله بتركيا، الناس بتركيا هلق.
English Translation: Well, in Turkey, people are in Turkey
now.
Arabic: بتركيا؟
English Translation: In Turkey?
Arabic: بتركيا.
English Translation: In Turkey.
Arabic: عمي احكي لي عن وضع الناس هون، شلون وضع الناس هون؟
English Translation: Uncle, tell me about the situation of
the people here, how is their situation?
Arabic: والله وضعهم يعني شوي في غلا يعني.
English Translation: Well, their situation, I mean, things
are a bit expensive.
Arabic: في غلا.
English Translation: Things are expensive.
Arabic: إيوه.
English Translation: Yes.
Arabic: على إيش عايشين الناس هون؟ على إيش معتمدين؟
English Translation: What are the people living on here?
What do they rely on?
Arabic: والله معتمدين ع الزراعة.
English Translation: Well, they rely on agriculture.
Arabic: عالزيتون ما زيتون، كرم، رمان، شغلات هيك يعني.
English Translation: Agriculture.
English Translation: On olives and such, vineyards,
pomegranates, things like that.
Arabic: إيش اللي بيميز الناس هون؟
English Translation: What distinguishes the people here?
Arabic: ها؟
English Translation: Huh?
Arabic: إيش اللي بيميز الناس هون؟
English Translation: What distinguishes the people here?
Arabic: شلون يعني؟
English Translation: What do you mean?
Arabic: يعني طبيعتهم، احكي لي عن طبيعتهم شلون؟
English Translation: I mean their nature, tell me about
their nature, how is it?
Arabic: طبيعتهم بيروحوا ع شغلهم وبيجوا وهيك يعني، فلاحين كان
أكثر شيء يعني.
English Translation: Their nature is they go to their work
and come back, like that, they were mostly farmers.
Arabic: وعالتجارة كمان.
English Translation: So their nature is farmers?
English Translation: And in trade as well.
Arabic: عالتجارة.
English Translation: In trade.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله، يا أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: And peace and mercy of God be upon you,
welcome.
Arabic: الله يسلمك.
English Translation: May God bless you.
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
Arabic: أنا ماني من أبناء المنطقة ها.
English Translation: I am not from the region, you see.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا فيك، من وين إن كنت تكون؟
English Translation: You are welcome, wherever you may be
from.
Arabic: آه طبعا أكيد.
English Translation: Are you Syrian?
English Translation: Oh, of course, absolutely.
Arabic: من وين حضرتك؟
English Translation: Where are you from?
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا فيك.
English Translation: I am from Hama.
English Translation: Welcome to you.
Arabic: الله يسلمك.
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
Arabic: احكي لي عن الناس هون، تعاملهم، يعني معيشتكم أنتم
اندماجكم هون بهالمجتمع.
English Translation: Tell me about the people here, their
interactions, I mean your livelihood, your integration here
in this society.
Arabic: بشكل عام الشعب هون شعب راقي جداً جداً.
English Translation: In general, the people here are very,
very refined people.
Arabic: ولا لا تقلي إنه كردي أو عربي لا لا لا، ما بيعرفوا
هالميزة.
English Translation: And don't tell me whether it's Kurdish
or Arab, no, no, no, they don't know this distinction.
Arabic: لا أنا ما قلت، أنت قلت.
English Translation: No, I didn't say that, you did.
Arabic: لا أنا اللي عم قلك إياها، هن كرد وعرب.
English Translation: No, I'm the one telling you this, they
are Kurds and Arabs.
Arabic: ولكن الالتحام الديني أول شيء الإسلامي، هاي أول شغلة.
English Translation: But the religious bond is the first
thing, the Islamic one, that's the first thing.
Arabic: ثانياً يعني تعامل جيد جداً.
English Translation: Secondly, I mean, the interactions are
very good.
Arabic: وما في هالعنصرية ما بنعرفها ما شفناها، أنا واحد ناس
يعني إلي سنتين معهم هون.
English Translation: And there is no such racism, we don't
know it, we haven't seen it. I am one of the people who have
been with them here for two years.
Arabic: أنا الأخ أعتبره أخ وحسين أنا جاري، جاره من سنتين.
English Translation: I consider the brother here a brother,
and Hussein is my neighbor, I have been his neighbor for two
years.
Arabic: بكل الألفة، بكل المحبة، بكل المودة، عايشين مع بعضنا
بكل شيء بيخطر ببالك من جمال للمنطقة.
English Translation: With all familiarity, all love, all
affection, we live together with everything beautiful about
the region you can think of.
Arabic: والأمان جيد جداً، مشاكل ما فيه.
English Translation: And safety is very good, there are no
problems.
Arabic: ولكن بس الميزة إنه ما في شغل بس، الناس يعني دون خط
الفقر بس.
English Translation: However, the only issue is that there
is just no work, people are simply below the poverty line.
Arabic: أما ما تبقى يعني في أمان، في ألفة بين الناس، في
وحدة، في محبة.
English Translation: But as for the rest, there is safety,
there is familiarity among people, there is unity, there is
love.
Arabic: يعني حتى إذا بدنا نحكي عالجيش يعني ترى أموره جيدة
جداً جداً.
English Translation: I mean, even if we talk about the army,
their situation is very, very good.
Arabic: الشباب المستلمين هون بكل لباقة بكل كل شيء بيخطر
ببالك.
English Translation: The guys in charge here act with full
courtesy and everything you can imagine.
Arabic: لو قلت لك عد لي ثلاث صفات بتميز أهالي بعدنلي.
English Translation: If I asked you to list three traits
that distinguish the people of Ba'dinli.
Arabic: أجمل صفات فيهم الاحترام.
English Translation: Their most beautiful trait is respect.
Arabic: عندهم بشكل يعني بيحترموك ولو ما بيعرفوك.
English Translation: They have a way, I mean, they respect
you even if they don't know you.
Arabic: عندهم صفة الاحترام جميلة جداً.
English Translation: They have a very beautiful trait of
respect.
Arabic: عندهم المحبة إلك بدون ما يعرفوا مين أنت.
English Translation: They have love for you without knowing
who you are.
Arabic: ممتاز.
English Translation: Excellent.
Arabic: محبتهم كويسة كتير كتير كتير.
English Translation: Their love is very, very, very good.
Arabic: الميزة الأكثر إنهم كريمين مع الجار.
English Translation: The greatest trait is that they are
generous with their neighbors.
Arabic: ولو أنا، أنا واحد ناس يعني أعتبر غريب عن الضيعة،
يعني الكرم معهم شيء مميز عندهم.
English Translation: Even though I am someone considered a
stranger to the village, their generosity is something
distinctive about them.
Arabic: والثالثة؟
English Translation: And the third?
Arabic: هاي الثالثة اللي عم أعطيك إياها، عندهم الاحترام،
عندهم المحبة، عندهم الكرم.
English Translation: That's the third one I'm giving you:
they have respect, they have love, they have generosity.
Arabic: يا سلام، يا سلام.
English Translation: Oh wow, wow.
Arabic: بقي سؤال أخير، شو بتشتغل؟
English Translation: One last question remains, what do you
do for work?
Arabic: أنا ما بشتغل شيء.
English Translation: I don't work at all.
Arabic: متقاعد؟
English Translation: Are you retired?
Arabic: عايشين الحمد لله رب العالمين، عندي أولادي بيشتغلوا
من فضل الله تعالى.
English Translation: We are surviving, praise be to the Lord
of the worlds, I have my children working, by the grace of
God Almighty.
Arabic: والحمد لله رب العالمين أموري تمام التمام، الحمد لله
رب العالمين.
English Translation: And praise be to the Lord of the
worlds, my affairs are perfectly fine, praise be to the Lord
of the worlds.
Arabic: الله يسلمك ويبارك فيكم وبارك الله فيكم وأهلا وسهلا
مية سلامة، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God give you strength.
Arabic: الله يسلمك ويبارك فيكم وبارك الله فيكم وأهلا وسهلا
مية سلامة، أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God keep you safe and bless you,
and may God bless you, welcome, a hundred greetings,
welcome.
Arabic: محمد إبراهيم أو أبو الزعيم كما هو معروف في بعدنلي،
English Translation: Mohammed Ibrahim, or Abu Al-Zaeem as he
is known in Ba'dinli,
Arabic: إحدى الشخصيات المميزة جداً في هذه القرية والمحبوبة.
English Translation: is one of the very distinguished and
beloved personalities in this village.
Arabic: ويسمونه الدامرجي أي الحداد المبدع، لأنه يعمل منذ 40
عاماً في الحدادة في مختلف أنواعها،
English Translation: They call him Al-Damirji, meaning the
creative blacksmith, because he has been working for 40
years in various types of blacksmithing,
Arabic: الحدادة المنزلية، وتصنيع الآلات الزراعية، وأيضا
تصنيع الآلات الصناعية من الحديد.
English Translation: household blacksmithing, manufacturing
agricultural machinery, and also manufacturing industrial
machines from iron.
Arabic: سنكون معكم مع العم أبو الزعيم لنتعرف على هذه الشخصية
وأيضاً على أهم إنتاجه في مجال الحدادة، تابعونا.
English Translation: We will be with you alongside Uncle Abu
Al-Zaeem to get to know this personality and also his most
important productions in the field of blacksmithing, stay
tuned.
Arabic: يا رب.
English Translation: Oh Lord.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا بك.
English Translation: Welcome to you.
Arabic: الله يعطيك العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا مع السلامة.
English Translation: Welcome, go in peace.
Arabic: اسمح لي أقعد جنبك.
English Translation: Allow me to sit next to you.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا مية سلامة.
English Translation: Welcome, a hundred greetings.
Arabic: شو عم تساوي؟
English Translation: What are you doing?
Arabic: والله بدنا نقص حديد بدنا نلحم.
English Translation: Well, we want to cut iron, we want to
weld.
Arabic: الله يعطيك العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health.
Arabic: أهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: Welcome.
Arabic: إيش هذا اللي بإيديك؟
English Translation: What is that in your hands?
Arabic: هذا بنسة لحام، بنسة لحام.
English Translation: These are welding pliers, welding
pliers.
Arabic: هذا، هذا شو هذا؟
English Translation: This, what is this?
Arabic: هذا كرسي موتور.
English Translation: This is a motor mount.
Arabic: اه كرسي موتور عم تصلحه.
English Translation: Oh, a motor mount you are fixing.
Arabic: إم.
English Translation: Yes.
Arabic: قد إيش صار لك بهالمهنة؟
English Translation: How long have you been in this
profession?
Arabic: 40 سنة.
English Translation: 40 years.
Arabic: 40 سنة! ما شاء الله.
English Translation: 40 years! Mashallah.
Arabic: من وين إجا حبك لهالمهنة وشغلك فيها؟
English Translation: Where did your love for this profession
and your work in it come from?
Arabic: أنا، أنا عسكري، عسكري إيه.
English Translation: Me, I am a soldier, a soldier, yes.
Arabic: أنا كنت بالشام مع تموين الشام.
English Translation: I was in Damascus with the Damascus
supply department.
Arabic: كنت أشتغل هنيك.
English Translation: I used to work there.
Arabic: إيه يعني اشتغلت بالحدادة المنزلية بإيش اشتغلت؟
English Translation: Yeah, meaning you worked in household
blacksmithing, what did you work on?
Arabic: هنيك منزلية واشتغلت بلبنان إيه.
English Translation: There household, and I worked in
Lebanon, yes.
Arabic: تعلمت هنيك شيء جديد يعني؟
English Translation: Did you learn anything new there, I
mean?
Arabic: من عندي اه.
English Translation: From myself, yes.
Arabic: احكي لي عن تاريخك بالحدادة.
English Translation: Tell me about your history in
blacksmithing.
Arabic: يعني أهل الضيعة هون بيعتبروك إنت يعني علم.
English Translation: I mean, the people of the village here
consider you, like, an icon.
Arabic: تقريباً.
English Translation: Almost.
Arabic: كل العالم بيحبوني وأنا بحب كل العالم.
English Translation: Everyone loves me and I love everyone.
Arabic: شو السبب؟ الله هيك يكثر المحبة يا رب.
English Translation: What's the reason? May God increase the
love like this.
Arabic: أنا ما بكره لحدا.
English Translation: I don't hate anyone.
Arabic: ما في شخص بكرهه.
English Translation: There is no person that I hate.
Arabic: حلو كتير.
English Translation: That's very nice.
Arabic: بس إنت محبوب لأنك إنسان مخلص في مهنتك.
English Translation: But you are loved because you are a
person dedicated to your profession.
Arabic: إي والله كل واحد بيجي شلون بحب بكون، يرجع رضيان
ومبسوط.
English Translation: Yes by God, everyone who comes, however
they like it to be, they go back satisfied and happy.
Arabic: تمام.
English Translation: Perfect.
Arabic: هلق إنت بديت في الحدادة المنزلية، حدادة البيوت،
الأبواب والشبابيك ولا بإيش بديت؟
English Translation: Now, you started in household
blacksmithing, blacksmithing for houses, doors, and windows,
or what did you start with?
Arabic: بالأول شبابيك وبواب بعدين هون بالتريلات، خلف
الجرارات، صهاريج مي، آلات زراعية كله.
English Translation: At first windows and doors, then here
with trailers, the backs of tractors, water tanks,
agricultural machinery, all of it.
Arabic: ما شاء الله، كل هدول اشتغلت فيهم؟
English Translation: Mashallah, you worked on all of these?
Arabic: مطاحن رصاص.
English Translation: Lead grinders.
Arabic: مطاحن، مطاحن، طحن بطاريات رصاص.
English Translation: Pardon?
English Translation: Grinders, grinders, grinding lead
batteries.
Arabic: ما شاء الله، طحن بطاريات!
English Translation: Mashallah, grinding batteries!
Arabic: طحن رصاص، مطاحن رصاص، إيوه.
English Translation: Grinding lead, lead grinders, yes.
Arabic: وسمعت كمان إنه إنت يعني شاغل آلة تقشير جوز، مطحنة
سماق.
English Translation: And I also heard that you, I mean, have
worked on a walnut peeling machine, a sumac grinder.
Arabic: ها، هذا هو.
English Translation: Yes, this is it.
Arabic: هذا هو؟
English Translation: This is it?
Arabic: هيدي الأفكار إنت يعني من عندك ولا إنت بتشوف آلات
وبتقلدها؟
English Translation: Are these ideas yours, or do you see
machines and copy them?
Arabic: بس إذا تطلعت عالشيء بطلع مثله وأحسن.
English Translation: I just have to look at something, and I
make something like it or better.
Arabic: بس اطلعت عالشيء.
English Translation: You just have to look at something.
Arabic: ما بتتعذب بإنتاجه؟
English Translation: You don't struggle to produce it?
Arabic: 40 سنة.
English Translation: 40 years.
Arabic: 40 سنة!
English Translation: 40 years!
Arabic: طيب فرجيني هلق هيدي، فهمني عالـ، احكي لي عن هي شوي،
تقشير الجوز.
English Translation: Alright, show me this now, explain to
me about the, tell me a bit about this, the walnut peeling.
Arabic: إذا ممكن بس تطفي لنا شوي المولدة عشان نقدر نحكي.
English Translation: If possible, just turn off the
generator for us a bit so we can talk.
Arabic: هذا مولدة، بيركب هون دينامو.
English Translation: This is a generator, a dynamo is
attached here.
Arabic: إيوه.
English Translation: Yes.
Arabic: مشان يبرم من تحت.
English Translation: So that it rotates from the bottom.
Arabic: إم.
English Translation: Mm.
Arabic: بس إذا برم هذا بيشتغل هيك.
English Translation: As soon as it rotates, this works like
this.
Arabic: بيقشر جوزات.
English Translation: It peels walnuts.
Arabic: بيقشر الجوز هيك؟
English Translation: It peels walnuts like this?
Arabic: وبيطحن السماق كمان؟
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: And it grinds sumac too?
Arabic: إيه بيقشر سماق، بيساوي حب.
English Translation: Yes, it peels sumac, turns it into
seeds.
Arabic: يعني أنا بفهم من كلامك بإنو إنت إنسان تبدع ما يسد
احتياجات المنطقة، آلات زراعية؟
English Translation: So I understand from your words that
you are a person who creates what meets the needs of the
region, agricultural machinery?
Arabic: كل شيء حديد بيمشي عندي.
English Translation: Everything iron works for me.
Arabic: وكيف هيك يعني الحديد بصير بين إيديك مطواع ولين
وبتشكله عكيفك، احكي لي؟
English Translation: And how does iron become pliable and
soft in your hands and you shape it as you like, tell me?
شو ما بدي بيصير.
Whatever I want, happens.
شو السبب؟ يعني ايش العلاقة بينك وبين الحديد؟
What is the reason? I mean, what is the relationship between
you and iron?
والله محبة، إلي هواية كتير بالحديد.
Well, love, I have a big hobby for iron.
طيب، إنت عم تستعمل معدات حديثة في الطعج واللي والكسر ولا
شلون؟
Alright, are you using modern equipment for bending,
twisting, and breaking, or what?
والله أكتر شيء ع الإيدين، بس شغل بدو طعج بعفرين عم نساوي،
جاهز عم نجيبه، منطبقه.
Well, mostly by hand, but work that needs bending we do in
Afrin, we bring it ready, and assemble it.
طبعاً انت جاهز بتجيبه؟ حالياً في أماكن يعني بتشتغل فيها
بتطعج أو كذا هيك؟
Of course, you bring it ready? Are there places you work in
currently for bending or such things?
لا عندي ما في آليات، إمكانيات ما عندي.
No, I don't have machinery, I don't have the capabilities.
في المنطقة فيه؟
Is there any in the area?
بعفرين.
In Afrin.
بعفرين؟ إنت عم بتصنع قلت لي فطورات، وصهاريج، وتريلات؟
In Afrin? You told me you manufacture cultivators, tanks,
and trailers?
تريلات، وصهاريج مي، وكلفاتورات، وسكك، تصليحات، كل شيء حديد
تصليح بصلح.
Trailers, water tanks, cultivators, plows, repairs, I fix
everything made of iron.
كله بتصلحه؟ إيش في عندك غير هيدا هون فرجيني؟
You fix it all? What else do you have here, show me?
في كلفاتور بس ما طبقته، عم جهزه.
There is a cultivator but I haven't assembled it, I am
preparing it.
خلينا نشوفه.
Let's see it.
هدول تمان سياخ بده يركب.
These eight rods need to be installed.
هيدا تقريباً، مو من زمان طلع، هيدا موديل حديث تقريباً
بيقولوا له.
This is approximately, it didn't come out long ago, they
call it a modern model roughly.
ممم.
Mmm.
وهدول زنود إله، بس عم نطبقه، لسه ما صار جاهز.
And these are arms for it, we are just assembling it, it's
not ready yet.
هذا تصنيعك هذا؟
Did you manufacture this?
لأ، عم نجيبه جاهز، هيدا شغل معمل.
No, we bring it ready, this is factory work.
هدول بده يركبوا عليه، وفي شاسيه تاني ورا الدكان.
These need to be mounted on it, and there is another chassis
behind the shop.
هذا أعتقد مناسب لطبيعة الأرض تبعكم، إنه أرض قراجية جبلية، مو
هيك؟ مرن شوي، هدول راصورات للمرونة.
I think this is suitable for the nature of your land, as
it's rocky mountainous land, isn't it? It's a bit flexible,
these are springs for flexibility.
إيوا، مرينات كتير.
Yes, they are very flexible.
شقد بيحتاج منك هيك مثلاً، قلت لي فطور شغل، هيك سكة؟
How long does such a thing take you, you said working on a
cultivator, such a plow?
يعني صناعته؟
You mean its manufacturing?
إي شقد بيطول معك؟
Yes, how long does it take you?
أسبوع.
A week.
أسبوع كامل.
A whole week.
اليوم هالمهنة، هالمهنة هيدي بتطعمي خبز؟ إيش وضعها؟
Today, this profession, does this profession feed you bread?
What's its situation?
لا المهم واحد بيستر، بس ما يحتاج لحدا، بيكفي.
No, the important thing is one covers his needs, as long as
he doesn't need anyone, it's enough.
قصدي يعني بيمر بهاليوم؟ ما في طلب عليها؟
I mean, is it going through these days? Is there no demand
for it?
طلب في، في حركة.
There is demand, there is movement.
كم حدا بيشتغل معك؟ كم شب بيشتغل معك هون؟
How many people work with you? How many young men work with
you here?
والله تنين كانوا يشتغلوا معي، بس هلأ عندهم شغل شوي.
Well, two used to work with me, but now they have a bit of
work.
إي.
Yes.
من جماعة جيش الحر.
From the Free Army group.
هذا مثقب؟
Is this a drill?
مثقب عامودي.
A vertical drill.
هذا كهربائي وهذاك كهربائي؟ ما عندك شيء يدوي؟
This one is electric and that one is electric? Do you have
anything manual?
يدوي ما في.
There is no manual.
وهذا جلخ كهربائي.
And this is an electric grinder.
احكي لي ولادك ورثوا هالمهنة؟
Tell me, did your kids inherit this profession?
والله ما لهم هواية، كله دراسة، تعليم مدرسة.
Well, they have no hobby for it, it's all studies, school
education.
كم ولد عندك الله يخليهم؟
How many kids do you have, may God keep them?
سبعة.
Seven.
سبعة، ما شاء الله. شو درسوا؟
Seven, Masha'Allah. What did they study?
والله ما شفت جو، شلون صار، كلهم انقطعوا، وصلوا اتنين جامعة
وبطلوا.
Well, you see the atmosphere, how it became, they all
stopped, two reached university and quit.
حسبي الله ونعم الوكيل، هنن معك هون؟
God is sufficient for us, and He is the best disposer of
affairs. Are they with you here?
والله كل واحد مطرح. واحد بالدنمارك، واحد ببريطانيا، ناس
بحلب، ناس هون.
Well, everyone is in a different place. One is in Denmark,
one in Britain, some in Aleppo, some here.
يعني إنت صامد هون؟
So you are steadfast here?
فرض، شو بدي أساوي.
It's an obligation, what can I do.
الله يعينك. الحجة إيش وضعها؟
May God help you. How is the Hajja doing?
والله وسط.
Well, average.
شلون وسط قلي؟
What do you mean average, tell me?
كويس، كويسة، الحمد لله.
Good, she is good, thank God.
وإنت صحتك شلون؟
And how is your health?
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
قديش عمرك؟
How old are you?
والله تقريباً خمسة وستين.
Well, roughly sixty-five.
خمسة وستين؟ مو مبين عليك، جد مو مبين عليك. السبب إنه إنت
عملك بالحديد، ما شاء الله عطيك هيك يعني عزم وصحة ووجهك، ما
شاء الله عليك.
Sixty-five? You don't look it, you really don't look it. The
reason is that you work with iron, Masha'Allah, it gives you
strength, health, and your face, Masha'Allah.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
كله بياد الله.
It's all in God's hands.
كل شيء بياد الله.
Everything is in God's hands.
أكيد، لا إله إلا الله. اتفقت معك مية بالمية. الله يحفظك
ويحميك يا رب.
For sure, there is no god but Allah. I agree with you a
hundred percent. May God protect and keep you.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
ويقويك كمان.
And give you strength too.
أهلاً وسهلاً، مية سلامة، إنتو والجماعة كلها، على راسي وعلى
عيني.
Welcome, a hundred greetings, you and the whole group, you
are on my head and eyes.
الله محييك، شكراً أخوي أبو الزين.
God greet you, thank you my brother Abu Al-Zein.
أهلي وسهلين، مية سلامة، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, a hundred greetings, welcome.
على الرغم من وجود مغاور ومعاصر قديمة، إلا أن عمر قرية بعدنلي
لا يزيد عن 400 عام في أفضل تقدير...
Despite the presence of ancient caves and presses, the age
of Ba'dinli village does not exceed 400 years at best...
عندما جاءت عشيرة الشيخان بمنطقة بهدينان، الواقعة بين العراق
وإيران، وسكنت في هذه المنطقة، وعملت في الزراعة.
...when the Shikhan tribe came from the Bahdinan region,
located between Iraq and Iran, and settled in this area,
working in agriculture.
للحديث عن تاريخ قرية بعدنلي، يسرنا أن يكون ضيفاً معنا في هذه
الفقرة الأستاذ مصطفى خليل، أحد أبناء هذه القرية والمهتم
بتاريخها، تابعونا.
To talk about the history of Ba'dinli village, we are
pleased to have Mr. Mustafa Khalil as our guest in this
segment, one of the village's sons and a history enthusiast.
Stay tuned.
أستاذ مصطفى يعطيك العافية.
Mr. Mustafa, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, welcome.
إنت من أبناء بعدنلي، ومهتم بتاريخها.
You are one of the sons of Ba'dinli, and interested in its
history.
نعم.
Yes.
نحن الآن وين واقفين؟
Where are we standing right now?
واقفين في المنطقة البلدة القديمة، أقدم بيوت في بعدنلي، هذا
البيت من أقدم البيوت في بعدنلي.
We are standing in the old town area, the oldest houses in
Ba'dinli, this house is one of the oldest in Ba'dinli.
أقدم بيت، يعني قديش عمره؟
The oldest house, I mean, how old is it?
عمر البيت من 400 سنة. وللوراء يعني حتى التاريخ اللي قبله ما
بعرف، بس 400 سنة تحديداً نعرف.
The house's age is 400 years. And going further back, I mean
even the history before it I don't know, but 400 years
specifically we know.
400 سنة. طيب، احكي لي قصة هالضيعة، تاريخها، يعني من وين بدأ؟
400 years. Okay, tell me the story of this village, its
history, I mean, where did it begin?
بدأ تاريخ البعدنلي من 400 سنة، أجدادنا إجوا سكنوا هون من
منطقة بهدينان.
The history of Ba'dinli began 400 years ago, our ancestors
came and settled here from the Bahdinan region.
نعم.
Yes.
منطقة بهدينان الواقعة بين حدود إيران وعراق. سبب المجيء إلى
هالمنطقة، شح الأمطار ونقص المياه...
The Bahdinan region, located on the borders between Iran and
Iraq. The reason for coming to this area was the scarcity of
rain and lack of water...
بما إنو الإنسان متعود ع الزراعة، وعلى الرعي، فدائماً الإنسان
متوجه للمنطقة اللي فيها الكسرة بالمي والزراعة.
Since people were accustomed to agriculture and grazing, a
person is always drawn to an area with an abundance of water
and farming.
بينما هون الأسس اللي انبنى عليها بعدنلي، المنطقة القديمة
هون، في عدة عوائل أتوا مع بعضهم، وهي عشيرة الشيخان من منطقة
البهدينان.
Meanwhile, the foundations on which Ba'dinli was built here,
the old area, several families came together, and they are
the Shikhan tribe from the Bahdinan region.
نعم، غير الشيخان؟
Yes, anyone other than the Shikhan?
عشيرة الشيخان هي منطقتنا المعروفة، تسكن أو تقطن في 40 قرية
ضمن منطقة راجو.
The Shikhan tribe is our well-known area, living or residing
in 40 villages within the Rajo region.
بعدنلي وحدة من هدول القرى؟
Ba'dinli is one of those villages?
بعدنلي وحدة من هاز القرى.
Ba'dinli is one of these villages.
قبل، قبل ما يجوا من بهدينان، ما كان في حدا هون ساكن؟
Before, before they came from Bahdinan, was there anyone
living here?
ما، ما كنا نعرف. لجدودنا إجوا، ما قبل هالتاريخ ما بنعرف.
We didn't know. Our ancestors came, we don't know anything
prior to this date.
ما بتعرف. طيب، هنن كانوا يعني يمتهنون الزراعة ورعي
الحيوانات؟
You don't know. Alright, were they practicing agriculture
and animal herding?
الزراعة وحيوانات.
Agriculture and animals.
زراعة وحيوانات.
زراعة الزيتون، العنب، قبل كان في مي بكثرة، يزرعوا القطن،
القمح، الشوندر، كل شيء بالزراعة كانوا يزرعوه بهالمنطقة هون.
Farming olives, grapes. Previously, there was plenty of
water; they used to plant cotton, wheat, sugar beet. They
farmed everything agricultural in this area here.
كان في هون ينابيع مياه؟
Were there water springs here?
كان ينابيع مياه، مثلاً في هون عنا جبل بيسمونه جبل النمر، فيه
لحد هلا ينبوع، لحد هلا جارية المي فيها.
There were water springs. For example, here we have a
mountain called Tiger Mountain, which still has a spring to
this day, the water is still flowing in it.
وينابيع بعيدة عنا، نحن بنقول سهل بعدنلي، ينابيع لحد هلا
جارية، وكميات وفيرة.
And springs far from us, in what we call the Ba'dinli Plain,
springs that are still flowing to this day, with abundant
quantities.
وفيرة. طيب خليني أسأل، يعني عشيرة الشيخان اللي إجت وسكنت
يعني في 40 قرية من قرى راجو، استوطنت هون، هون كان مركز
المشيخة تبعها؟
Abundant. Alright, let me ask, the Shikhan tribe that came
and settled in 40 villages of the Rajo villages, settling
here, was this the center of its sheikhdom?
لا مو ضروري المركز المشيخة، الضرورة إنه هون كانت المي وفيرة،
والزراعة، والرعي، نحن بنسميه المرعى للحيوانات، كان هون وفيرة
يعني المراعي والخضار والحشيش كله مليء، يعني وفير.
No, it wasn't necessarily the center of the sheikhdom. The
necessity was that water was abundant here, as well as
agriculture, and grazing, what we call pasture for animals;
it was abundant here, meaning pastures, greens, and grass
were all plentiful, abundant.
أنا معك، بس يعني مركز يعني العشيرة، زعامة العشيرة وين صارت؟
I am with you, but I mean the center of the tribe, where was
the leadership of the tribe?
العشيرة كان شيخ الرش آغا، منطقة جوميت. وبعدها تحولت المشيخة
إلى كورا أحمد، هو الساكن في بعدنلي...
The tribe's sheikh was Al-Rash Agha, in the Jumit area. Then
the sheikhdom transferred to Kora Ahmad, who lived in
Ba'dinli...
وبعدها خليل بيك استلم المشيخة، وبعدها عزت آغا استلم المشيخة،
والآن الموجود خليل، خليل عزت، موجود هو الآغا، المنطقة.
...and then Khalil Bey took over the sheikhdom, and after
him, Izzat Agha took over the sheikhdom, and currently, it's
Khalil, Khalil Izzat, who is the Agha of the region.
حسب معلوماتي إنه أظن يعني ما قبل خليل آغا، يعني كان شخص أخد
رتبة البكاوية من العثمانيين، ومن ثم أظن إنه خليل آغا كان
أيضاً عضو في البرلمان السوري في الخمسينات؟
According to my information, I think, before Khalil Agha,
there was a person who took the rank of Bey from the
Ottomans, and then I think Khalil Agha was also a member of
the Syrian Parliament in the fifties?
الجد عزت آغا، كان عضو في البرلمان سنة 1957، دام فيها أربع
سنين.
The grandfather Izzat Agha, was a member of parliament in
the year 1957, lasting for four years.
وبعدها خليل، خليل عزت دام في الإدارة المحلية محافظة حلب على
دورتين، تمان سنين ضل في الإدارة المحلية.
And then Khalil, Khalil Izzat remained in the local
administration of Aleppo Governorate for two terms; he
stayed in the local administration for eight years.
وقبل ذلك؟
And before that?
قبل ذلك خليل بيك أخد البكاوية من العثمانيين، وكنا هداك الوقت
تابعين لولاية كلس. ولاية كلس، يعني كل أمورنا الإدارية ولاية
كلس.
Before that, Khalil Bey took the rank of Bey from the
Ottomans, and at that time we were subordinate to the
Wilayah of Kilis. The Wilayah of Kilis, meaning all our
administrative matters were in the Wilayah of Kilis.
وكانت الحدود مفتوحة بين سوريا وتركيا.
And the borders were open between Syria and Turkey.
نعم كانت الحدود مفتوحة، ذهاب وإياب لا ما في حدود بيناتنا
كان.
Yes, the borders were open, going back and forth, no, there
were no borders between us.
الآن إنتو تابعين لناحية راجو؟
Now you are subordinate to the Rajo sub-district?
نحن تابعين لناحية راجو الآن.
We are subordinate to the Rajo sub-district now.
علاقاتكم الاقتصادية والتجارية مع مين؟
Who are your economic and commercial relations with?
كضمن الناحية، نحن عنا بازار بعدنلي وفي براجو، وفي، علاقاتنا
الناحية السجل المدني كل شيء تابع لراجو نحن.
Within the sub-district, we have the Ba'dinli bazaar, and in
Rajo, and our sub-district relations, civil registry,
everything is subordinate to Rajo for us.
علاقة اقتصادية مع عفرين؟
Economic relations with Afrin?
مع عفرين، مع جميع المناطق.
With Afrin, with all regions.
معبطلي، عفرين، شران، جنديرس، جميع المحافظات القريبة منا،
اعزاز، دارة عزة، ادلب، يعني بشكل موسع. احكيلي عن اهم العوائل
الموجودة في القرية وطبيعة العلاقة بيناتهم.
Mabata, Afrin, Sharran, Jindires, all the neighboring
governorates, Azaz, Darat Izza, Idlib, basically on a wide
scale. Tell me about the most important families in the
village and the nature of the relationship between them.
اهم العوائل في بعدنلي، عائلة كور احمد، عائلة بيت علي، بيت
حجي، دميسو، هدول العائلات الاساسيين اللي كانوا موجودين،
وبعدها تم اللجوء الى قرية بعدنلي او اتوا بعد فترة في عوائل
كثيرة اجوا ع بعدنلي.
The most important families in Badinli: the Kor Ahmad
family, the Beit Ali family, Beit Hajji, Dâmiso. These are
the main families that were present, and then there was
refuge to the village of Badinli, or they came after a
period, many families came to Badinli.
من وين اجوا؟
Where did they come from?
من الضيع القريبة، يعني من ضيعة شران، من ضيعة بلبلة.
From the nearby villages, meaning from the village of
Sharran, from the village of Bulbul.
نواحي عفرين؟
Afrin districts?
نواحي عفرين.
Afrin districts.
كلهم اكراد؟ سكان الاهل القرية كلهم اكراد؟
All of them are Kurds? The inhabitants of the village are
all Kurds?
كلهم اكراد.
All of them are Kurds.
مافي عرب، مافي تركمان، مافي ابدا؟
No Arabs, no Turkmen, nothing at all?
كلهم سكان اصليين. كلهم سكان اصليين، اكراد.
All are original inhabitants. All are original inhabitants,
Kurds.
كيف كان، يعني كيف كان شكل العلاقة بيناتهم كعوائل؟
How was, meaning how was the nature of the relationship
between them as families?
كعلاقات اخوة وجيدة جدا، وكلياتهم كانوا مشتركين مع بعض،
الدليل لذلك ان المنطقة القديمة او البلدة القديمة كانت
متوحدة، يعني حتى البيوت مافي بيناتهم اي فراغ، نسبة للحب
والاخوة بيناتهم.
Like relations of brotherhood and very good, and all of them
were shared together, the proof of that is that the old area
or the old town was united, meaning even the houses had no
space between them, due to the love and brotherhood between
them.
طيب، هذا الجامع، بس بدي اسألك عن هذا الجامع، قديش عمره؟
Okay, this mosque, I just want to ask you about this mosque,
how old is it?
الجامع، ما يقارب مئتين سنة، كان اعمار قديم، والان نحن كاهالي
بعدنلي حدثنا فيه، والحمدلله وصل لهالمرحلة.
The mosque, approximately two hundred years old, it was an
old construction, and now we as the people of Badinli
modernized it, and thank God it reached this stage.
المئذنة قديش عمرها، خلينا...
The minaret, how old is it? Let us...
المئذنة، المئذنة عمرها...
The minaret, the minaret is...
خليك واقف، نكون ورا الجامع لو سمحت، وقف هون، نعم.
Stay standing, let's go behind the mosque please. Stand
here, yes.
المئذنة تعمرت على مرحلتين، اول مرحلة قرابة 80 سنة، والمرحلة
التانية قرابة 70 سنة. على مرحلتين.
The minaret was built in two stages. The first stage was
nearly 80 years ago, and the second stage nearly 70 years
ago. In two stages.
مرحلتين. لكن عمر الجامع بالعموم اقل من 200 عام؟
Two stages. But the age of the mosque in general is less
than 200 years?
نعم اقل من 200 سنة.
Yes, less than 200 years.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك، اهلا وسهلا، سلامة، وشكرا الكم.
May God give you health, welcome, safe travels, and thank
you.
بيوت قرية بعدنلي مبنية على سفح جبل ومتجهة باتجاه الجنوب
والشرق.
The houses of Badinli village are built on the foot of a
mountain and face south and east.
وهي مركبة فوق بعضها البعض على شكل طبقات تناسب تكوين الهضبة
الجبلية.
They are stacked on top of each other in layers that suit
the formation of the mountainous plateau.
وهي تتنوع ما بين البيوت القديمة جدا التراثية والبيوت الحديثة
والبيوت التي تأخذ الصفتين معا.
They vary between very old traditional houses, modern
houses, and houses that combine both characteristics.
سنكون معكم في هذه الفقرة في زيارة لبيت الحاجة فاطمة دميرل
لنتعرف عليها وعلى نموذج بيتها القديم. تابعونا.
We will be with you in this segment on a visit to the house
of Hajja Fatima Demirel to get to know her and the model of
her old house. Follow us.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh Lord. Peace be upon you.
اهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
حياك الله. شلونك؟
God bless you. How are you?
مرحبا يا حجة.
Hello Hajja.
اهلا اهلا.
Welcome, welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمدلله.
Praise be to God.
بدي ابرك جنبك.
I want to sit next to you.
الحمدلله.
Praise be to God.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
والله الصحة ما ضل... تعبانين.
By God, health is gone... tired.
ما ضل. شو عم تقول؟
Gone. What is she saying?
عم تقول الصحة ما فيها العافية، يعني تعبانة كتير.
She's saying health doesn't have wellness, meaning she's
very tired.
سلامتك. قديش عمرك؟
Get well soon. How old are you?
Emrê te çiqas e?
How old are you?
Nod heye? Na, na... lê.. pênc û şêst... nizanim.
Is it ninety? No, no... but.. sixty-five... I don't know.
عمرا 90 سنة.
Her age is 90 years.
90 سنة؟ ما شاء الله، ما شاء الله.
90 years? Mashallah, mashallah.
انتي صاحبة هالبيت؟
Are you the owner of this house?
Xwediyê vê malê tu yî?
Ha?
Huh?
Nê.
Yes.
صاحبة هالبيت؟
The owner of this house?
Xwediyê vê malê tu yî?
Are you the owner of this house?
Ha, erê, belê, ez im.
Ah, yes, yes, it's me.
اللي عمرو، زوجك الحجي، الله يرحمه؟
The one who built it, your husband the Hajji, may God have
mercy on him?
Yê ku ev çêkiriye, mêrê te Qadir bû, rehma Xwedê lê be?
The one who built this, was it your husband Qadir, may God
have mercy on him?
Ha, mêrê min, mêrê min çêkiriye.
Ah, my husband, my husband built it.
الزوج اسمه قادر، هو اللي عمر.
The husband's name is Qadir, he is the one who built it.
هي عم تحكي باللغة الكردية.
She is speaking in the Kurdish language.
هي عم تحكي هلق باللغة الكردية.
She is speaking now in the Kurdish language.
Bapîrê min ev der da wî, wî jî li ser ava kir.
My grandfather gave this place to him, and he built on it.
عم تقول انه جدي تبرعلو بالمحضر هون ليعمر عليه.
She is saying that my grandfather donated the plot here to
him to build on it.
قديش عمر هالبيت؟
How old is this house?
Emrê vê malê çiqas e?
Ez nizanim, kuro.
I don't know, boy.
حوالي 71 سنة.
About 71 years.
71 سنة.
71 years.
من وين جابوا هالحجر؟
Where did they get this stone from?
Ev kevir ji ku anîn? Kevirên ku ew pê...
Where did they bring this stone from? The stones that
they...
Nav zeytûnan de derdixistin.
They were extracting them from the olive groves.
بين الزيتون بيقلعوا الحجر...
From among the olive trees they extract the stone...
وبيضبطوه وجايين معمرين هون.
And they prepare it and came to build here.
الحجة زوجها... واشتغلوا بهالطريقة هي، يعني هاد الحجر هني
ضربوه...
The Hajja and her husband... and they worked in this way,
meaning this stone, they shaped it...
Kê çêkir? Ev yê ku nexşandiye...
Who built it? The one who decorated it...
Yê çêkiriye... Haşîno çêkiriye.
The one who built it... Hashino built it.
في واحد عنا معمرتي اسمه حشينو...
There is a builder here named Hashino...
معمرجي كان قديم ببعدنلي، وواحد من قرية حمشلك، اللي عمروه
واللي ضبطوا هالحجر.
He was an old builder in Badinli, and one from Hamshalak
village, who built and prepared these stones.
تنيناتن توفوا.
Both of them passed away.
هاد البيت في قبو؟
Does this house have a basement?
Qebûya jêr heye li vir de?
Is there a basement down here?
Bin wê hemû wisa ye.
Everything underneath it is like that.
في غرفة هون تحت، في قبو.
There is a room down here, there is a basement.
طيب، لما بنوا هاد البيت، هاد البيت كان على اطراف بعدنلي ولا
كان بقلب بعدنلي؟ لانه هلق حاليا تقريبا يعني في البساتين...
في الكروم...
Okay, when they built this house, was this house on the
outskirts of Badinli or was it in the heart of Badinli?
Because now it's currently almost, you know, in the
orchards... in the vineyards...
Wextê we ev mal çêkir, malên li vir hebûn?
When you built this house, were there houses here?
Na.
No.
ما كان في بيوت طاولة.
There were no houses at all.
اي كيف؟
So how was it?
Bes ew ên jor... yên mala wî hebûn.
Only those up there... those of his house were there.
Kê?
Who?
Yên jor lo... temam...
The ones up there, boy... okay...
Mala Bekrî Berî?
Bekri Beri's house?
Birakê Xelîl Elî çêkiribû lo. Mistê Elî lo...
Khalil Ali's brother had built it, boy. Miste Ali, boy...
Mistê Elî.
Miste Ali.
كان في بيت وحيد هون، بيت مصطفى علي، وهنن البيت التاني اللي
عمروه، وبقية البيوت ما كانت موجودة.
There was only one house here, Mustafa Ali's house, and they
were the second house they built, and the rest of the houses
weren't there.
هاد البيت من اقدم البيوت هلق في بعدنلي؟
Is this house one of the oldest houses currently in Badinli?
Ev ji kevnarên gundê B'adîna ye? Ev xaniyên kevn in?
Is this one of the ancient ones of Badina village? Are these
old houses?
Havê kevnarê wî malê ye... ev hewşên kevn in, ji mêj ve ye.
This is the ancient one of that house... these are old
courtyards, from a long time ago.
هني معمرينو، قديم.
They built it, it's old.
ايش في عندها اولاد؟
How many children does she have?
Çend zarokên te hene?
How many children do you have?
Welle heft qîzên min hene û sê lawên min hene.
By God, I have seven girls and I have three boys.
سبع بنات وتلات صبيان... وتلاتة توفوا.
Seven girls and three boys... and three passed away.
ما شاء الله، ما شاء الله. الله يرحمهن وان شاء الله هيك يطول
عمر الطيبين.
Mashallah, mashallah. May God have mercy on them and God
willing, prolong the lives of the good ones.
وهي عمرا 90؟
And her age is 90?
هي عمرا 90 سنة.
Her age is 90 years.
هي عم تقول 90؟
She is saying 90?
ايه.
Yes.
Emrê te çiqas e? Nod e?
How old are you? Ninety?
Na, na.
No, no.
Doxê... ko ew mirî emrê te şêst e... te digot heştê salî
me...
Wait... when he died you were sixty... you said I'm eighty
years old...
Xalî... qederê... belkî... heştê... heştê û heşt salî me.
Uncle... about... maybe... eighty... I am eighty-eight years
old.
Heştê û heşt teqrîben.
Eighty-eight approximately.
يعني بحدود 80... 90 سنة، 88-90 سنة.
Meaning around 80... 90 years, 88-90 years.
مين ساكن معها بهالبيت؟
Who lives with her in this house?
Kî bi te re li vir rûniştiye?
Who lives with you here?
Ez û lawekî xwe rûniştine.
Me and my son are living here.
هي وابنها.
She and her son.
طيب تسمحيلنا نتفرج عالبيت؟
Okay, will you allow us to look around the house?
Tu destûrê didî me em hundirê malê bigerin?
Do you allow us to wander inside the house?
Bi ser çavan, ferman e... sêretan bikişînin û...
By all means, it's an order... take pictures and...
اهلا وسهلا، على راسي.
Welcome, on my head.
Baş e... hûn bi xêr hatin...
Okay... you are welcome...
يا لحظات، تفضل.
Oh moments, please go ahead.
هلق هون مكتوب حنان، حنان حسين... حسين 1959.
Now here it is written Hannan, Hannan Hussein... Hussein
1959.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
هون كأنه عبارة عن بيت... واحد، بس مقسوم قسمين.
Here it seems like it's a house... one, but divided into two
parts.
مقسوم الى قسمين.
Divided into two parts.
غرفة طويلة... ومقسومة الى قسمين.
A long room... and divided into two parts.
سقفه عادي، لكن... يعني مو سقف خشب ولا اقواس.
Its roof is normal, but... meaning not a wooden roof nor
arches.
تم التحديث في كل القرية... تم التحديث، كان اولي كل البيوت
خشب، وقناطر... بس تم التعديل فيه.
It was modernized in the whole village... it was modernized,
initially all the houses were wood, and arches... but it was
modified.
لكن الحيطان هي كلين مزدوج؟
But the walls are dual block?
كلين مزدوج، 60 سانتي تقريبا الحيطان القديمة، العمار قديم
كله، سماكة الحيطان 60 سانتي... والسقوفة كان خشب...
Dual block, approximately 60 centimeters for the old walls,
the construction is all old, the thickness of the walls is
60 cm... and the roofs were wood...
خشب... في جب هون؟ في... جب...
Wood... is there a well here? There is... a well...
جب مي. تفضل.
A water well. Go ahead.
تمام. الله يعطيكن العافية.
Perfect. May God give you health.
اهلا وسهلا. شكرا الكن.
Welcome. Thank you.
شكرا يا حجة. الله يعطيكي العافية.
Thank you Hajja. May God give you health.
Teşekkür ederim, teşekkür ederim.
Thank you, thank you.
اهلا وسهلا فيكي، شكرا الك.
Welcome, thank you.
الحجة بدها تقول كلمة بالتركي... يعني بتتشكركن يعني.
The Hajja wants to say a word in Turkish... meaning she is
thanking you.
بتحكي تركي؟
Do you speak Turkish?
Ben mektep...
I school...
بتكتبي بالتركي؟
Do you write in Turkish?
Tabii... Her şeyi biliyorum, mektep okudum orada.
Of course... I know everything, I studied at school there.
مكتب وين؟
School where?
Türkiye... Malatya.
Turkey... Malatya.
ملاطيا.
Malatya.
يا اهلا وسهلا فيكي.
You are very welcome.
Allah salimak.
May God keep you safe.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
شلونك يا حجي؟
How are you Hajji?
الحجي حاجتك؟
Are you done, Hajji?
حاجتك؟
Are you done?
اي نعم.
Yes indeed.
عنك.
Let me do it for you.
شرف.
Come in.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمدلله.
Praise be to God.
ايش الحلو بهالضيعة؟ بعدنلي ايش فيها حلو؟ تحكيلي عن الحلو
ببعدنلي.
What's nice about this village? What's nice in Badinli? Tell
me about the nice things in Badinli.
اشنو مو حلو؟ شعبو مليح... مسلمين... وامانة... وتعيش معو...
يعني بكل سهولة...
What is not nice? Its people are good... Muslims... and
trustworthy... and you live with them... meaning with all
ease...
بسهولة...
With ease...
نعم... بكل سهولة، ضيعتنا غير ضيعة... هالضيعة...
Yes... with all ease, our village is unlike any other
village... this village...
شلون؟
How so?
يعني اخلاقو مليح... بتتحمل الاذى بتتحمل الصبر يعني...
Meaning its morals are good... it endures harm, it endures
patience meaning...
...b-il'alem. Ya'nî sît kethîr ya'nî. Bi-tîcara b-yişghil
b-il'alem.
...with the world. I mean, a lot of fame. Engaging in trade
with the world.
Lî'ennu b-tiştaghlû bit-tîcara b-tit'amalû ma'al 'alem
kwayyes?
Because you work in trade, you deal with people well?
Ey na'am. Eyye.
Yes, indeed. Yes.
L-qura llî hawalaykun?
The villages around you?
Na'am. Kem na'am. Min... 'anna yîcî hetta Şam û ya'nî...
bîsawî tîcara... m'allaq bîcî min kethîr 'alem.
Yes. How many, yes. From... we have people coming even to
Damascus, and I mean... doing trade... connected, it comes
from a lot of people.
Hallaq întu bî-i'tibar b-tiştaghlû fit-tîcara, ya'nî
l-mehasîl z-zira'iyya.
Now, considering you work in trade, meaning agricultural
crops.
Na'am.
Yes.
B-trûhû 'alal qura llî hawalaykun b-tiştrû minhum mehasîl?
Do you go to the villages around you and buy crops from
them?
Mitl eyş?
Yes.
Like what?
Mitl l-coz, l-loz, l-kerm, yabraq, tirşî ya'nî hamid.
Like walnuts, almonds, vineyards, grape leaves, pickles,
meaning sour.
Hamid.
Sour.
Eyy.
Yes.
W z-zeytûn w z-zeyt?
And olives and oil?
Z-zeytûn w z-zeyt 'anna bîcî b-tiştirî min... bîsawî tîcarî
ya'nî bî'abbî ya'nî bîkassir... bîsawî mrabba w hadiyye.
Olives and oil, we have them come, you buy from... doing
trade, meaning filling, meaning crushing... making jam and
gifts.
T-tîn w l-'inab?
Figs and grapes?
Na'am. T-tîn w l-'inab... şimalî bîsawî zbîb, dibis.
Yes. Figs and grapes... in the north they make raisins and
molasses.
L-yom t-tîcara l-maşye eyş hiyye?
Today, what is the ongoing trade?
Hallaq weqt... l-coz.
Now is the time... for walnuts.
L-coz?
Walnuts?
Na'am.
Yes.
Weqtu, ey na'am. Weqt l-coz w weqt l-'inab bîsawî zbîb.
Is it its time now?
Its time, yes indeed. The time for walnuts, and the time for
grapes to make raisins.
Smi't înnu fî 'andkun sûq xass bis-summaq?
I heard you have a special market for sumac?
S-summaq... xelas weqtu. Ya'nî...
Sumac... its time is over. Meaning...
Xelas. Bas 'andkun sûq las-summaq?
It's over. But you have a market for sumac?
Na'am.
Yes.
'Andkun. W fî 'andkun sûq lal haywanat? Dawab?
You do. And do you have a market for animals? Livestock?
La', b-nrûh 'a Raco.
No, we go to Rajo.
B-trûhû 'a Raco b-itbî'û l-haywanat?
You go to Rajo to sell the animals?
Na'am. Eywa. Raco... w hwnîke.
Yes. That's right. Rajo... and there.
Hwnîke.
Over there.
Na'am.
Yes.
Hon eyş huwe ya'nî lamma bîyîcî d-deyf la'andkun...
Here, what is it like, I mean when a guest comes to you...
Eyş b-itdayyfû awwal ma bîyîcî lahon?
What do you serve them as soon as they come here?
B-ndeyyfu?
What do we serve them?
Ey.
Yes.
Îllî ş-şî 'andu fî mitl... hallaq mitl l-'inab.
Whatever he has, like... right now, like grapes.
Ya'nî hasab l-mawsim.
Meaning according to the season.
Na'am.
Yes.
L-mawsim l-hader b-itdayyfû?
You serve them whatever the current season is?
Na'am.
Yes.
Ene qesdî ma b-itdayyfû şay, qehwe?
I mean, don't you serve tea and coffee?
Eyy tab'an, hada şay w qehwe had ferz. Mû sunnî, ferz.
Yes of course, tea and coffee are obligatory. Not a
tradition, obligatory.
Ferz, mû sunnî!
Obligatory, not a tradition!
Na'am. Lî'ennu îza wahid... ma b-hibbak ma b-yîcî 'andak.
Ktîr b-ydeyyef... w d-duyûf ahsan. Îza înte mû teyyib ma
b-yîcî 'andak. Lazim t-qaddim lû.
Yes. Because if someone... doesn't like you, they won't come
to you. They are very hospitable... and guests are better.
If you are not good, they won't come to you. You must offer
to them.
D-deyf deyf l-lah.
The guest is the guest of God.
Allah akbar.
God is great.
'Andkun hon l-mey, meyyet d-dey'a...
Do you have water here, the village's water...
Na'am.
Yes.
B-tişrabû min l-abar, ya'nî min l-cibab? Meyyet l-metar?
Do you drink from wells, meaning from cisterns? Rainwater?
Hada teba' l-metar w b-yîcî min... teba' hukûme yîcî.
This is from the rain and it comes from... the government's
supply comes.
Min l-hukûma b-yîcî.
It comes from the government.
Na'am.
Yes.
Allah ya'tîk l-'afîye 'ammî 'Arif.
May God give you health, Uncle Arif.
Ahla w sehle w mîyyet... Allah yû'afîk, elf 'afîye.
Welcome and a hundred... May God give you health, a thousand
healths.
Allah yusallimak u yitewwil 'umrak u yahfazak.
May God keep you safe, prolong your life, and protect you.
Allah yahfazak. B-ahkîlak wahid... qissa.
May God protect you. Let me tell you a... story.
Eyy.
Yes.
Ya rabbî şeffi' fîna nebîna, fî yewmin nus'al 'amma ceneyna.
O Lord, let our Prophet intercede for us, on a day we are
asked about what we have committed.
Nahnu nîyyatna taht l-xetaya, qed a'tarafna zat l-'etaya.
We, our intentions are beneath sins, we have confessed to
the Lord of gifts.
Îza lem tudrik minka l-'înaya, fe men haza yu'wî lîl-
muznibîna.
If care from You does not reach us, then who is there to
shelter the sinners?
Haza nu'ammil eyya rehîmu, min bahr l-'afwî wa l-'amîmu.
This is what we hope for, O Merciful, from the sea of pardon
and general grace.
Fe la tuxeyyib lî-men narûmu, wa l-babu meftûh lîl-qasidîna.
So do not disappoint the one we seek, and the door is open
for the seekers.
Ya rabbî şeffi' fîna nebîna, fî yewmin nus'al 'amma ceneyna.
O Lord, let our Prophet intercede for us, on a day we are
asked about what we have committed.
'Ala şems z-zatî ya mewlaya sellî, lî-dînî eyyid w alû bihî.
Upon the sun of the essence, O my Lord, send blessings,
support my religion, and upon his family.
Haza meqamun 'abdun yusellî, 'ala Muhammed Taha l-emîna.
This is the station of a servant who prays, upon Muhammad,
Taha the trustworthy.
Allahumma salli 'ala n-nabî. Allah ya'tîk l-'afîye ya 'ammî.
O Allah, send blessings upon the Prophet. May God give you
health, uncle.
Allah yû'afîk.
May God give you health.
Şukran îlak.
Thank you.
Ahlan wa sahlan. Allah ma'ak.
You are welcome. God be with you.
Ma'a l-'amm 'Arif tentahî cawlatu hazal usbû' min qaryat
Ba'dînlî fî rîf Raco.
With Uncle Arif, this week's tour ends from the village of
Ba'dinli in the countryside of Rajo.
Mintaqat 'Efrîn rîf Heleb aş-şemalî.
Afrin district, northern countryside of Aleppo.
Sanakûnu ma'akum fî l-asabî' l-qadima fî cawlat cadîda min
manatiq sûriya ukhra habîba.
We will be with you in the coming weeks on a new tour from
other beloved Syrian regions.
Lî-mutaba'at bernamicina tabî'û safhat l-face xassa bi
l-qanat.
To follow our program, follow the channel's specific
Facebook page.
Wa aydan mewqi'ana 'ala l-internet halabtodaytv.net.
And also our website on the internet, halabtodaytv.net.
As-salamu 'alaykum wa rahmatullah wa barakatuh.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[Music]